<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>news on Universal</title>
    <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/categories/news/</link>
    <description>Recent content in news on Universal</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://datascience.utu.fi/categories/news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>European Bioconductor Meeting 2020</title>
      <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/blog/2020/12/04/2020-12-04-eurobioc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datascience.utu.fi/blog/2020/12/04/2020-12-04-eurobioc/</guid>
      <description>Presentations at EuroBioc2020 At the European Bioconducutor Meeting EuroBioc2020, Dec 14-18, 2020, we will give a short talk, birds of a feather session, and a poster on the emerging R ecosystem for microbiome research.
Dedicated class structures are fundamental for the R/Bioconductor ecosystem. In microbiome research, the phyloseq class has become a commonly accepted standard. However, recent developments in Bioconductor classes and growing sample sizes have opened up new opportunities and requirements to extend this popular format in order to address emerging research needs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparing evolutionary processes in nature and society</title>
      <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/blog/2020/12/03/2020-12-03-kone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datascience.utu.fi/blog/2020/12/03/2020-12-03-kone/</guid>
      <description>Comparing evolutionary processes in nature and society New support from KONE foundation for a joint project led by Ass. Prof. Indrė Žliobaitė.
The world is changing at unprecedented rates. Financial crises, epidemics, climate disasters and military conflicts rise suddenly and change common ways of living. We can no longer hope to learn how the world is, by the time we learn, the world has changed. We need to focus on process-level understanding of how the world is changing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>rOpenGov website renewed and new hetu R package published!</title>
      <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/blog/2020/12/02/2020-12-02-ropengov/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datascience.utu.fi/blog/2020/12/02/2020-12-02-ropengov/</guid>
      <description>New rOpenGov homepage and hetu R package The rOpenGov project homepage for open government data analytics has now moved to a new address, and substantially revised. Read more at https://ropengov.org/!
In addition, the new hetu R package for Finnish identification numbers (persons, companies) has been released.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New nominations</title>
      <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/blog/2020/12/01/2020-12-01-nominations/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datascience.utu.fi/blog/2020/12/01/2020-12-01-nominations/</guid>
      <description>PI Leo Lahti has been nominated for the following:
  Finnish National Board on Research Integrity (TENK) Research integrity advisor in University of Turku for the
  National open science coordination steering group
  Finnish Society for Computer Science board
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New papers</title>
      <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/blog/2020/11/21/2020-10-22-pub/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datascience.utu.fi/blog/2020/11/21/2020-10-22-pub/</guid>
      <description>Recent publications   Prebiotic Xylo-oligosaccharides Targeting Faecalibacterium prausnitzii Prevent High Fat Diet-induced Hepatic Steatosis in Rats with Lensu et al.
  Eicosanoid Inflammatory Mediators Are Robustly Associated With Blood Pressure in the General Population by Palmu et al.
  Association Between the Gut Microbiota and Blood Pressure in a Population Cohort of 6953 Individuals by Palmu et al.
  Unsupervised hierarchical clustering identifies a metabolically challenged subgroup of hypertensive individuals by Vaura et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Algorithmic openness in decision-making</title>
      <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/blog/2020/11/20/2020-10-21/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datascience.utu.fi/blog/2020/11/20/2020-10-21/</guid>
      <description>Recent writings related to the openness of epidemic models used to support decision-making by the Finnish government.
  August 19, 2020 Avoimuus voi vahvistaa päätöksenteon tieteellistä pohjaa
  June 26, 2020 Päätös epidemialaskelmien salaamisesta vastoin valtioneuvoston avoimuuslinjausta
  June 22, 2020 Lähdekoodin sisältämien yksityiskohtien avoimuus on keskeistä päätöksenteon läpinäkyvyydelle
  May 15, 2020 Tietopyyntö epidemialaskelmien lähdekoodeista
  May 3, 2020 Laskentamallit eivät lähtökohtaisesti ole salassa pidettävää tietoa</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/blog/2020/11/01/2020-11-01-posts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datascience.utu.fi/blog/2020/11/01/2020-11-01-posts/</guid>
      <description>New people  Oct 1, 2020: Tuomas Borman started as a research assistant, welcome! Aug 18, 2020: Pyry Kantanen joined the rOpenGov developer team, welcome! July 20, 2020: Tim Garrels joins our team through the Baltic Science Network Mobility Programme for Research (BARI) Internship June 1, 2020 Guilhem Sommeria-Klein joins the team!  Funding   Sep 1, 2020 Academy of Finland consortium Eco-evolutionary mechanisms underlying critical transitions in microbial communities now launched!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DHN2020 award</title>
      <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/blog/2020/10/22/2020-10-22-dhn/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datascience.utu.fi/blog/2020/10/22/2020-10-22-dhn/</guid>
      <description>Wrangling with non-standard data by Mäkelä et al. selected as best long paper in DHN2020!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2019 news</title>
      <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/blog/2019/12/31/2019-12-31/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datascience.utu.fi/blog/2019/12/31/2019-12-31/</guid>
      <description>Dec 23, 2019 Leo Lahti joined as arXiv moderator (applied statistics)
Dec 16-20, 2019 Statistical research in microbiome research workshop in Pune, India
Dec 7, 2019 Research talk in Savitribai Pule Pune University by Leo Lahti on microbiome bioinformatics.
Nov 29, 2019 Ville Laitinen received the best presentation award in Turku Computational Life Science annual seminar!
Nov 29, 2019 Moein Khalighi received a PhD study position in Turku. Congratulations!
Nov 26, 2019 Integrating open science in the humanities - the case of computational history</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2018 news</title>
      <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/blog/2018/12/31/2018-12-31/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datascience.utu.fi/blog/2018/12/31/2018-12-31/</guid>
      <description>12 December
Published A Quantitative Approach to Book-Printing in Sweden and Finland, 1640–1828
12 December
Significantly improved CRAN release for the pxweb R package. Automated access to data from dozens of statistical authorities globally.
11 December
Leo Lahti nominated to Digital Humanities advisory board by National Library of Finland
6 December
Presentation on microbiome data science at European Bioconductor Meeting 2018 in Munich (Slides (PDF)).
5 December
Best oral poster for Anna Aatsinki in Turku Computational Life Science meeting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open science award</title>
      <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/blog/2017/12/31/2017-31.12/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datascience.utu.fi/blog/2017/12/31/2017-31.12/</guid>
      <description>December 2017: Open Science and Research award of the Ministry of Education and Culture for Open Knowledge Finland Open Science work group!</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
