<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Olds on Turku Data Science Group</title>
    <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Olds on Turku Data Science Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="http://datascience.utu.fi/old/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/contact/</guid>
      <description>Test test
   Email leo.lahti@iki.fi

&amp;ndash;&amp;gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/publications/</guid>
      <description>The complete bibliography is available in BibTex. You can find most papers and other outputs from here, or just ask by email.
For code, data, and audiovisual material see the separate code and media pages.
 Selected papers {% bibliography &amp;ndash;file bibtex/lahti &amp;ndash;query @*[keywords=highlight] %}
Computational biosciences {% bibliography &amp;ndash;file bibtex/lahti &amp;ndash;query @[status=bioscience] %} {% bibliography &amp;ndash;file bibtex/lahti &amp;ndash;query @[status=datascience] %}
Digital humanities and computational social science {% bibliography &amp;ndash;file bibtex/lahti &amp;ndash;query @*[status=dh] %}</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About the website</title>
      <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/aboutwebsite/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/aboutwebsite/</guid>
      <description>Make your own Jekyll website for your academic research group This website is powered by Jekyll and uses some Bootstrap and Bootswatch. The page borrows open source code from Allan Lab. The site is simple yet adaptable.
All pages are written in markdown for easy editing, and Jekyll uses Liquid for the data-driven pages. The publication list is automatically generated from bibtex, and requires the jekyll-scholar plugin. The news items, and group members are stored as .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blog</title>
      <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/blog/</guid>
      <description>{% for post in site.posts %} {% capture y %}{{post.date | date:&#34;%Y&#34;}}{% endcapture %} {% if year != y %} {% assign year = y %} {{ y }} {% endif %} {{ post.date | date:&#34;%Y-%m-%d&#34; }} {{ post.title }}  {% endfor %}  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CV</title>
      <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/cv/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/cv/</guid>
      <description>I embed a current version of my CV below. You can also download the PDF here.
{% include embedpdf.html code=&amp;ldquo;30ah9tgxevj1vl9/svm-cv.pdf&amp;rdquo; width=100 height=800 %}</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leo Lahti</title>
      <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/leo_lahti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/leo_lahti/</guid>
      <description>Links to academic services online: Leo Lahti 
Researcher profiles, networks, publication databases and impact altmetrics
 University of Turku Research Portal University of Helsinki TUHAT publication database ResearchGate ORCID: 0000-0001-5537-637X ResearcherID: G-3170-2010 ScienceOpen CiteUlike PubMed Google Scholar Scopus Publon reviewer profile ImpactStory Depsy research software impact Loop    </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Licensing</title>
      <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/licensing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/licensing/</guid>
      <description>Open licensing of scientific material This memo gives recommendations for selecting open source license for scientific material, including software, data and documents. Let us continue to make the newest computational techniques easily available to spark new applications and further development!
Recommended open licenses for academic publishing Software and source code The modified BSD licenses (in particular FreeBSD) and MIT license set minimal restrictions on the end user, and have therefore been recommended for academic purposes, for instance at ICML/MLOSS workshop 2010 (V.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>News</title>
      <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/allnews/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/allnews/</guid>
      <description>News {% for article in site.data.news %}
{{ article.date }} {{ article.headline }}
{% endfor %} </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publishing data and code</title>
      <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/publishing_code/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/publishing_code/</guid>
      <description>How to publish and archive research software or source code   Choose open license The code is not really &amp;ldquo;open&amp;rdquo; without an open license. Common ones include MIT, FreeBSD and GPL3. The MIT license is often recommended due to its simplicity. See Quick guide to software licensing for a scientist programmer. See also the brief memo on open licensing of scientific material.
  Add version number
  Document the experiments.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research / Old</title>
      <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/research/</guid>
      <description>Research topics Our research focuses on computational analysis of complex natural and social systems. There is a great demand for targeted computational techniques to extract information and insights from rich data collections based on clever combinations of human and machine intelligence. We blend elements from fields such as machine learning/AI, probabilistic programming, statistical ecology, and data science, and drive open developer communities that help to translate latest theoretical advances into accessible methods to inform modeling, experimentation, and decision-making.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research seminar</title>
      <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/seminar/</guid>
      <description>Seminar on machine learning and data science We are running a weekly research seminar and journal club on machine learning and data science in University of Turku, Finland. These are open and informal events. The exact location and topics may vary, so contact us if you&amp;rsquo;re interested!
Research seminar / Reading circle Thursdays 10-11:30am (2018-2019). We cover material from the following books, a chapter per week.
Machine learning - a probabilistic perspective (K.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turku Data Science</title>
      <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/docs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/docs/</guid>
      <description>Turku Data Science group site has moved to datascience.utu.fi</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turku Data Science Group - Home</title>
      <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/home/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/home/</guid>
      <description>Modern data analysis from theory to practice
We carry out research on theory, methods and applications of modern algorithmic data analysis, blending elements from various fields including statistical machine learning/AI, probabilistic programming, data science, and information engineering.
Our methodologically oriented research is motivated by data-rich applications that range from molecular life sciences to computational social sciences and humanities (SSH) research. Turku Data Science Group is led by Associate Prof. Leo Lahti.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vacancies</title>
      <link>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/vacancies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datascience.utu.fi/old/vacancies/</guid>
      <description>Open positions We are always looking for new group members with passion, talent, and grit!
PhD and Postdoc positions If you are interested in working with us as a PhD student or postdoc, please send me an email. State briefly why you are interested and attach a CV, including information about the grades you had as an undergraduate. Important: please insert &amp;ldquo;Application PhD&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Application Postdoc&amp;rdquo; in the subject line.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
